<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>The Opt Out Project</title>
    <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra" />
    <updated>2022-10-04T12:42:38-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The Secrets to My Success</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/the-secrets-to-my-success/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/the-secrets-to-my-success/</id>
            <category term="Philosophy"/>

        <updated>2022-10-03T19:30:02-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    In 2017 tech reporter Kashmir Hill reported on an experiment trying to opt out of Google, Facebook and Amazon. She&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>In 2017 tech reporter Kashmir Hill reported on an experiment trying to opt out of Google, Facebook and Amazon. She set up a blocker on her router so no sites affiliated with the big three could get through, essentially locking herself out of the internet. She put away her smartphone and found herself without the key tools of daily life. At one point she spent ages on a New York street corner trying desparately to get back into her apartment. This all made for great writing as it all bordered upon the absurd. Finally she gave up, declaring that you cannot live without big tech.</p>
<p>Kashmir and I spoke years ago after I went viral for concealing a pregnancy from the Internet. I like her and I always appreciate her reporting.</p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">But in this she did us all a disservice. The idea is now firmly planted in people's heads that you simply cannot opt out of Big Tech. It's too hard, they're too big and too pervasive. It's also way too inconvenient: no one wants to be locked out of their apartments, or the Internet for that matter. People have given up.</span></p>
<p>This is wrong, and it does us a disservice. It strips us of our one major power: the power to choose, to vote with our feet. It robs us of the chance to write our own future, to invest in non-creepy alternatives. And it's untrue. Because you can opt out. I'm living proof. </p>
<p>So what did Kashmir get wrong? Where do we diverge?</p>
<h2>1. One system at a time, please</h2>
<p>Opting out takes planning and preparation. You will eventually build an entire alternative tech ecosystem from a new series of devices and services. But you cannot leap there all at once. It disrupts too many of your routines, throws too many proverbial babies out with bathwater, and doesn't allow you to build robust relationships or habits that will stick.</p>
<p>It's kind of like that scene in <em>Airplane</em> where the captain keeps saying, "Looks like I picked the wrong day to quit smoking!" A few minutes later, the same character says, "Looks like I picked the wrong day to quit drinking!" And a few moments after that, "Looks like I picked the wrong day to quit sniffing glue!"</p>
<p>No one battling an addiction can actually, honestly, beat multiple addictions at once. Addiction is behavioral as much as it is biological. You need time to change those routines and make sure the changes stick. And you have to have enough support so that you don't jump out of the frying pan -- then decide it was pretty cosy in there and you'd rather get right back in again.</p>
<p>First, I left Google services in 2012. I was dismayed at the change to their privacy policy that allowed them to aggregate all user data around a single profile -- that's enough to make anyone pinpointable in the data, regardless of whether or not it's "anonymized." (More on differential privacy elsewhere: it wasn't an option in 2012).</p>
<p>I left Facebook in early 2016. I used the same "<a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/how-to-the-tech-break-up/">break up</a>" <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/the-basics/">technique</a> but with a few additional twists. After a lot of experimenting with alternative systems, <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/sailfish-the-iphone-and-android-alternative/">I put away my last iPhone for good in 2017</a>. Each of these moments took planning, ensuring I had the right systems in place to leap to, so I wouldn't look back.</p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Leave Google, Facebook, and Amazon? Yes, sure, you can do that. Leave them </span><em style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">all at once</em><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">? You're setting yourself up to fail.</span></p>
<h1>2. It can't be all or nothing</h1>
<p>Perhaps surprisingly for someone who is pretty extreme about data privacy, I don't actually think we need to be so extreme. Kashmir even blocked sites hosted by the big services. Blocking Amazon W3 is like shutting off half the Internet; blocking Microsoft Azure and what are you left with? Geocities or something?</p>
<p>As much as I'd like to stop these companies from becoming the entire infrastructure to the Internet, I have to marshall my resources to do so. That means I'm going to start with a major part of their money-making business, what fuels their investments in cloud services and what helps them embed themselves into every website on the net.</p>
<p>That is, I want to break the personal data economy. And we can do that, one person at a time, if we just stop systems from knowing <em>everything </em>about us.</p>
<p>That's why I don't think we need to leave entirely. We can be selective. As long as you don't let a single platform track you across the web and build up a picture of you, then you are  Just divide your data up across services. Log out of the single log-ins. Set up Ghostery or Firefox containers, or another blocking system that makes it impossible for companies to track you from one site to another.</p>
<p>We can also obfuscate ourselves by messing with their data. Like my colleagues Finn Brunton and Helen Nissenbaum have done. The systems they've built, like AdNauseum, confuse the heck out of algorithms by collecting messy data. The companies can't see any signal when it's all noise.</p>
<p>If you really, really need to stay on Facebook, maybe because you are part of a birdwatching group that you love--well then, stay. Just stay <em>only</em> for the birdwatching! Delete the rest of your friends, remove the other data from your profile. Then join every birdwatching group there is. It's that simple.</p>
<p>Now all Facebook knows about you is that you love birdwatching. They can't serve you Liberal or Conservative ads, or influence you to vote for someone, or show you comments from some high school friend you don't care about. Just birds! Trust me, you'll be a lot happier when you scroll. Especially if you're a bird person.</p>
<p>What does that do to Facebook? The power of "Meta" is how it tracks us across so many different parts of our lives. It does so with its single profile, its trackers embedded in our browsers when we log in, with all the data that we enter into it, including our statuses and our photographs. Oh, and by confusing us into forgetting that Facebook, Instagram, and WhatsApp are all actually the same company and therefore the same thing (more on tech gossip elsewhere).</p>
<p>To break that power, don't show them everything. Just, don't.</p>
<p>I left Meta but I still have a Twitter account. I got rid of all my other friends and just follow NASA people and open source systems. I don't stay logged in. I make sure that's all Twitter knows about me, and that's fine with me. You're welcome to follow me there, just don't be offended if I don't follow back.</p>
<p>3. Opting out is a moral imperative</p>
<p>This isn't just a personal experiment. I am a conscientious objector, and I believe we must opt out. We are already living through the dangers that were promised by embracing <em>these </em>technologies (not <em>all</em> technologies, these data-sucking algorithmic ones). It's a one-way street to social catastrophe.</p>
<p>And no, it's not the kind of creative "disruption" that's just the result of innovation. It's irresponsible. Its results are profitable but they are driving children to suicide, reinforcing racism in law enforcement, and fuelling genocide. It doesn't have to be this way.</p>
<p>But it won't be anything different if we don't make the choice. If we don't choose different systems, we'll keep feeding racist algorithms, manipulative governments, and body dysphoria just by the very act of logging in, liking, commenting and scrolling.</p>
<p>I wish I could say I had faith in regulation to take this problem away. But I don't. Maybe it's one too many clip making the rounds of a Senator "grilling" a social media guru. Like the time a congressman asked Mark Zuckerberg to turn off "Finsta." By all means, we need smart regulation, and quickly. But those guys aren't riding in on a white horse anytime soon. </p>
<p>In the meanwhile, it's up to us. Our actions matter. We can opt out, and we must. Like the environmental movement, making small changes in our lives can make a big difference.</p>
<p>Starting from a place of powerless isn't the way forward. Working together is. </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>My Privacy Policy</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/my-privacy-policy/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/my-privacy-policy/</id>

        <updated>2022-10-03T18:37:25-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I actually think we should all write ourselves a privacy policy: a terms of service list against which other companies&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I actually think we should all write ourselves a privacy policy: a terms of service list against which other companies need to measure up.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Who am I?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/who-am-i/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/who-am-i/</id>
            <category term="Philosophy"/>
            <category term="Basics"/>

        <updated>2022-10-04T12:20:21-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/13/tweet.png" alt="" />
                    I left Google in March of 2012, Facebook in early 2016. In 2014 I went viral for keeping a pregnancy&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/13/tweet.png" alt="" />
                <p>I left Google in March of 2012, Facebook in early 2016. In 2014 I went viral for keeping a pregnancy away from detection online. I still buy everything related to my children untraceably.  In my spare time I hack cell phones.</p>
<p>Why do all this?</p>
<p>I'm an expert in the relationship between technology and society. I'm a professor at Princeton University in the Sociology department, where I'm affiliated with Computer Science, the Center for Digital Humanities, and the Center for Information Technology Policy. I have a PhD in the study of science, technology, and society, which is actually a field. I research NASA's robotic spacecraft teams, studying how they work together and sometimes assisting them in organizing their teams for success.  I also publish in Human-Computer Interaction, alongside computer scientists.</p>
<p>It's this expertise that drove me to what I now call the Opt Out Experiments.</p>
<p>I've always been into computers. My dad brought our first one home in 1984, and I was hooked.  I had a reputation for being a computer geek and an early adopter. I even study robots in space!</p>
<p>But things changed once tech companies discovered they could mine user data for advertisting. Despite study after study showing the perilous road that Silicon Valley was on, companies refused to change their path, and people kept logging in. </p>
<p>Algorithmic recommenders. Filter bubbles. Predictive policing. Biased datasets. Manipulation. Persuasive design. All of it fueling and fueled by a rampant collection of personal data.</p>
<p>I was there as this was being developed and rolled out, and I saw the writing on the wall. Anyone with my training could see the technological dystopia we're currently enduring, coming from a mile away.</p>
<p>That didn't stop Silicon Valley from trampling all over those hard-won lessons from the history and sociology of technology. Maybe they thought we were just naysayers or Luddites instead of experts? As a result, people are still blissfully clicking and scrolling, and in so many predictable ways, the fabric of our society is fraying under the strain.</p>
<p>Amid all the heady rhetoric from Sillly Valley, it's easy to forget that technologies aren't some meteorite from outer space that hit "society," transforming it from out of nowhere (trust me, I study NASA, it's not that easy). Technologies are tools we build, along the lines of our choosing. The everyday devices in our pockets and on our desktops that are torquing our social world are just one vision among endless alternative possibilities. It could always be otherwise.</p>
<p>It still can. <span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">T</span>here are lots of ways to make digital devices, systems, and services <em>work</em>. Possibilities imbued with data stewardship and personal privacy. Tools that bring us a better, more harmonious, social world.  We can<span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> choose--and build--differently.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">That's why I started opting out.  </span>I have spent the last decade ditching toxic technologies, avoiding Big Tech's venomous tendrils like the plague. I did it all without living in a cave, throwing my devices away, or becoming a Luddite. I'm online, and my life is suffused with technologies. But I choose thoughtfully, ethically and responsibly. I'm not interested in if the latest blingy device comes in rose gold. Instead, I embrace companies and communities who help me to keep my data private, and to steer clear of those who don't. Sometimes I build things myself so that I know exactly where my data is.</p>
<figure ><figure class="post__image post__image--left"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/13/IMG_5374.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 100vw" srcset="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/13/responsive/IMG_5374-xs.JPG 300w ,https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/13/responsive/IMG_5374-sm.JPG 480w ,https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/13/responsive/IMG_5374-md.JPG 768w"  alt="I have a lot of alternative, old, or hackable phones. Here are a few of them." width="400" height="300"></figure>
<figcaption >Caption</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Since more and more people seem to want to know what I do and how to follow along, I started this site. I'll review some of my favorite tools and alternative options for you to consider. I'll share tips for how I manage my data in the face of an Internet hellbent on its lucrative extraction. I'll occasionally muse about what I've learned about Internet privacy while opting out. You can follow along online, and sign up for my mailing list to learn about fresh posts and ideas.</p>
<p>The opinions expressed here are entirely my own. I'm not paid for reviews of products, I'm just telling you what works for me. I'm not a journalist; I'm an academic, but I'll make every effort to make this readable. Also, since I'm all about data privacy and ownership, nothing on this website is stealing your data. You can browse, read, and subscribe in peace.</p>
<p>It's time for change. Techlash is rampant, people are angry at the FAANGs and tired of the Metaverse, Crypto, and the "next big thing." Fortunately, the power is in our hands. We can, truly can, leave these systems behind in the dirt. We can put our eggs in a better basket than this.</p>
<p>Let's get started.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How To: The Tech Break-Up</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/how-to-the-tech-break-up/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/how-to-the-tech-break-up/</id>
            <category term="Techniques"/>
            <category term="Basics"/>

        <updated>2022-09-28T13:42:36-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    How to leave products behind.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>How to leave products behind.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Divide (your data) and Conquer (Big Tech)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/divide-your-data-and-conquer-big-tech/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/divide-your-data-and-conquer-big-tech/</id>
            <category term="Techniques"/>

        <updated>2022-09-28T13:40:32-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Sailfish: the iPhone and Android Alternative</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/sailfish-the-iphone-and-android-alternative/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/sailfish-the-iphone-and-android-alternative/</id>
            <category term="Reviews"/>
            <category term="Phones"/>

        <updated>2022-09-28T13:41:21-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Google-Free Living (it&#x27;s better here)</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/the-best-non-google-search-engine/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/the-best-non-google-search-engine/</id>
            <category term="Search"/>
            <category term="Reviews"/>
            <category term="Basics"/>
            <category term="Apps"/>

        <updated>2022-09-29T19:01:03-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    People often ask me what I use instead of Google. The answer is: a lot of different systems. That's not&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>People often ask me what I use instead of Google. The answer is: a lot of different systems. That's not because Google is difficult to replace, per se. It's because I'm not about to give all my data to one system, whether that's Google or Yahoo!, Apple or Microsoft. I want my online data to be fractured, so that each company can only see one shard of my reflection in a broken mirror. I write more about this technique in my post on "data Balkanization," but in general, leaving Google means I'm not about to jump into bed with the next platform giant that comes along.</p>
<p>Also, before you get started leaving Google, be sure to read my post about the Tech Breakup. You can't just, edge your way out of the relationship with Google. Its tendrils are long. You have to be <em>prepared, </em>or leaving cold turkey is gonna leave you in the lurch, instead of Google. (Hint: they won't miss you. Better yet, you won't miss them.)</p>
<p>Key functionalities to replace on a daily basis? Search, email, browser, and maps, videos, calendars and file sharing. If you're a Chrome or Android person, then you're looking for a new operating system too: more on that in other posts. Each of these devices and services I've replaced with a different one--sometimes more than one service, if I want to keep my data safely segmented. I've spent a lot of time trying out many, many different systems. And I don't tend to keep my eggs in one basket.</p>
<p>In the coming months I'll do a more in-depth review of the services I know and love, things I've tried and tested.  I'll update this page with links when those posts go live. For now, though, here are the top contenders that I keep reaching for, time and again. </p>
<p>Before we get started, if you haven't yet deleted your GoogleID, then at least sign out of all Google services and clear your browser's cache.  Otherwise Google will follow you as you try out these alternatives. Which is missing the point.</p>
<h3>Search</h3>
<p>I've used lots of search engines, but I keep coming back to <a href="http://www.DuckDuckGo.com">www.DuckDuckGo.com.</a> Make it your homepage. They don't monetize based on aggregate search data, which is a fancy way of saying that they don't mine you for information, don't use your extracted data to profit on selling ads to your eyeballs, and don't put you in a filter bubble either. Plus DuckDuckGo has these cool search terms called "bangs," which is tech-speak for the exclamation mark. Search something with a "!m" and it'll search a map, with !v and it searches videos, !a pings Amazon. If you end up with a Google map or video on YouTube, it's through a proxy so Google can't track you. I've heard some people say they have trouble finding what they want on DuckDuckGo, but I've never had that problem. Maybe they're just so wrapped up in their filter bubble it looks like they can't find <em>what they want to see, </em>which is a different problem altogether and something I'm keen to avoid. Still, it I'm super curious about what people might be seeing on a Google search, I might run a search at <a href="http://www.startpage.com">www.startpage.com</a> which pings Google though a protective layer.</p>
<h3>Email</h3>
<p>The trick is to actually have lots of email addresses, but more on that later. I go with services that don't track or mine inboxes, like Protonmail.ch, Zoho.com, or self-hosted email (we do ours through <a href="http://www.ionos.com">www.ionos.com</a> webhosting). The cool thing about running your own email server is you can make unlimited addresses at will, so every company that wants your email address can have their own unique version.  That limits their ability to aggregate your personal data. You can also get a taste of this with new browser plugins from DuckDuckGo and Mozilla that make spoof email addresses for you to give away for discounts at the till, without risk of data </p>
<h3>Browser</h3>
<p>Chrome is a nightmare. You can build your own version using the Chromium kernel, or if the sentence I just wrote looks like gibberish to you then download Firefox already. When it comes to privacy and blockers, Mozilla has your back. Plus basically all your plugins on Chrome are available on Firefox too. Get off Chrome. It's a Google backdoor.</p>
<h3><strong><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">Maps</span></strong></h3>
<p>Years ago, when Apple Maps first came out and all the buildings in 3D view were rendering to look like the Leaning Tower of Pisa, I wrote a love letter to Apple Maps that got a lot of ridicule. I was just happy to see an alternative out there! I still use Apple Maps but also spread traces across Bing's mapping service, Pure Maps, Here.com, Open Street Maps, and Organic Maps.</p>
<h3>Videos</h3>
<p>I remember when YouTube was this weird video dating site that people didn't think would amount to much. Then it was acquired by Google. Now it's simply the biggest video sharing site in the world, and it's hard to avoid. When possible I get videos from places like Vimeo, but much of the time I just have to figure out how to get what I want from YouTube without them logging that I'm watching it. Searching for videos through DuckDuckGo using the !v function lets you play YouTube videos through their proxy, and you can always load up a VPN to browse from a fresh IP, load things in a private browsing window, and clear your cache often. Not being logged into Google or having any stable Google account goes a long way toward keeping them in the dark. If you're comfortable with the command line you can try <em>youtube-dl</em>, which will scrape and save a local copy of a YouTube video on your own computer. I mention it for completeness as this is not legal. But hey, it used to just be normal to watch things without being tracked by anyone. So for your next assignment, spend a little time wondering how we ended up in a situation where trying not to be tracked to allow people to make money off our eyeballs, is illegal. </p>
<h3>Calendars and other office stuff</h3>
<p>Most of the email services you will soon be signing up for to avoid Gmail will also come with a calendar. Apple has calendars too. Or you can try running your own. I love sandstorm.io which lets you run your own mini-server, keeping your data separated even from other systems you spin up on the same server.</p>
<p>I'll cover alternatives to Google Meet, gChat, and others in separate posts. And I will devote a lot of time to alternative phones, operating systems, and other home automation machines. Remember, this doesn't have to be an extreme form of digital veganism. You're just extracting your life from a platform giant, trying to spread your traces about, and share the love with systems that treat you and your data better.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Welcome to the Opt Out Project</title>
        <author>
            <name>Janet Vertesi</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/this-is-a-first-post-title/"/>
        <id>https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/this-is-a-first-post-title/</id>
            <category term="Techniques"/>
            <category term="Philosophy"/>
            <category term="Basics"/>

        <updated>2022-10-04T12:42:38-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    A provocative tip jar in NYC, circa 2014. Welcome, fellow and aspiring conscientious objectors! Yes, you can live a modern,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
    <figure class="post__image post__image--center">
      <img loading="lazy" src="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/1/Kahve_header.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 100vw" srcset="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/1/responsive/Kahve_header-xs.png 300w ,https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/1/responsive/Kahve_header-sm.png 480w ,https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/media/posts/1/responsive/Kahve_header-md.png 768w"  height="877" width="1400" alt="" />
      <figcaption>A provocative tip jar in NYC, circa 2014.</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h3 id="welcome-fellow-and-aspiring-conscientious-objectors">
      Welcome, fellow and aspiring conscientious objectors!
    </h3>

  <p>
    Yes, you can live a modern, digitally connected, twenty-first century life online without Big Tech. You don't have to trade your personal data for "free" services. It's not (always) technically difficult, and you don't have to live in a cave. I've done it, and you can too!
  </p>

  <p>
    I started this site to share the treasure trove of knowledge I've gleaned from over a decade of opting out of data-sucking services.
  </p>

  <p>
    You can start here with <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/basics/">the Basics</a>, learn more about the Opt Out project, delve into <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/the-basics/">the Techniques</a> I've developed to enable my lifestyle, or explore <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/the-tools/">the Philosophy</a>, the academically-informed thinking behind my unique approach.
  </p>

  <p>
    Or just jump into my reviews of alternative tools and systems: from <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/email/">email</a>&nbsp;and <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/phones/">search</a> to <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/phones/">cell phones</a>&nbsp;and the devices that power <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/tags/homesteading/">my connected home</a>.&nbsp;
  </p>

  <p>
    Or maybe you want to know who I am--I don't blame you!--more about that is <a href="https://cyberlyra.github.io/cyberlyra/who-am-i/">here</a> or on my professional website&nbsp;<a href="https://janet.vertesi.com" target="_blank">here</a>.
  </p>

  <p>
    It's time to reject toxic tech and usher in a better future. Let's get back in the drivers' seat, demand different tools, and start living a better life online.
  </p>

    <h3 id="dont-drop-out-opt-out">
      Don't drop out, opt out.
    </h3>

  <p>
    
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
